E-mail biancatrink@gmail.com

Phone +1 (520) 470-5822

Date of Birth April 10, 1978

Short Bio

I completed a MSc in Computer Science at the Federal University of the State of Rio de Janeiro in April 2016. Currently, I am a PhD Student and Research Assistant at the School of Informatics, Computing and Cyber Systems at Northern Arizona University, being awarded as the Outstanding Graduate Student on Spring 2021 and Finalist of Student Research Competition of International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE). I worked in IT industry from 2000 to 2019 as an IT Service Delivery Manager and Software and Infrastructure Project Manager. During the Master degree I researched about using measurement and strategies for IT Services.

My research is on the intersection of Software Engineering (SE), HCI and Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW). Currently, my main focus on increasing diversity in Open Source Software development, and how to attract and retain more women in Open Source. My interests revolve around Human Aspects of Software Engineering, Empirical Software Engineering and Data Analysis. I have experience on both quantitative and qualitative research, maturity models, measurement, OKRs and KPIs, applying the methods and approaches that are most suitable for the problem and research.

Education

Title	Year	Institution
P.hD. in Computer Science	2023	Northern Arizona University
	(Ongoing)	
M.Sc. in Computer Science	2016	Federal University of the State of Rio de Janeiro (UNIRIO),
		Brazil
M.B.A. in Computer Science	2012	Federal University of Rio de Janeiro (UFRJ), Brazil

Professional experience

Institution	Period	Position
Northern Arizona University (NAU), USA School of Informatics, Computing and Cyber Systems	2019 – present	Research Assistant
Vale S/A, Brazil IT Services	2011 – 2019	Cloud Services Delivery Manager
Rede D'Or Health Care, Brazil Project Management Office	2010-2011	Software and Process Improvement Project Manager
Cyberlynxx S/A	2005-2010	Software and Infrastructure Project Manager
	2000-2005	Senior System Admin

Publications

★ - indicates well-ranked/high-visibility venues in my area

Journal Papers

- ★2018 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, 2018, "SINIS: A GQM+Strategies-based Approach for Identifying Goals, Strategies and Indicators for IT Services". *Information and Software Technology*, v. 100, p. 147-164, 2018.
- 2015 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., "Evaluation of measurement process on a Global Organization under the light of MR-MPS-SV maturity model", iSys Brazilian Journal of Information Systems, vol 8 issue 2: pp. 58-77.

Peer Reviewed Conference and Workshop Papers

- 2021 FERREIRA, E., **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., "SINIS-LA Method for IT Alignment Considering Service Level Management". Brazilian Symposium on Information Systems (SBSI), Uberlandia, Minas Gerais, Brazil
- ★ 2021 SANTOS, F., WIESE, I., **TRINKENREICH, B.**, STEIMACHER, I., SARMA, A., GEROSA, M. "Can I Solve it? Identifying the APIs required to complete OSS tasks". Mining Software Repositories (MSR) Accepted and going to be presented on May 2021
- ★ 2021 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, "Please Don't Go Increasing Women's Participation in Open Source Software". Finalist of Student Competition of the 43rd International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE) Accepted and going to be presented on May 2021
- ★ 2021 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, "Please Don't Go Comprehensive Approach to Increase Women's Participation in Open Source Software". <u>Doctoral Symposium</u> of the 43rd International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE) Accepted and going to be presented on May 2021
- ★ 2021 GEROSA, M., WIESE, I., **TRINKENREICH, B.**, LINK, G., ROBLES, G., TREUDE, C., STEINMACHER, I., SARMA, A., 2021, "The Shifting Sands of Motivation: Revisiting What Drives Contributors in Open Source". 43rd International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE) Accepted and going to be presented on May 2021
- ★ 2020 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, GUIZANI, M., WIESE, I., SARMA, A., STEINMACHER, I., 2020, "Hidden Figures: Roles and Pathways of Successful OSS Contributors". 23rd **Computer Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)** (**Honored Mention Paper Award**)
- ★ 2020 BALALI, S., ANNAMALAI, U., PADALA, S., **TRINKENREICH, B.**, GEROSA, M., STEINMACHER, I., SARMA, A., 2020, "Recommending Tasks to Newcomers in OSS Projects: How Do Mentors Handle It?". 16th **International Symposium on Open Collaboration**. (**Best Paper Award**)
- ★ 2019 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., CONTE, T., "Combining GQM+Strategies and OKR Preliminary Results from a Participative Case Study in Industry". 20th **International Conference on Product-Focused Software Process Improvement (PROFES)**
- 2018 FERREIRA, E., **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., "Using SINIS and GQM+Strategies to Align Organizational Goals and Service Level Agreement Indicators". 17th Software Quality Brazilian Conference (SBQS), Curitiba, Brazil (Best Paper Award)
- ★ 2018 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., CONTE, T., "Defining, Measuring and Monitoring IT Service Goals and Strategies Practical Results and Pitfalls from a Qualitative Study in Industry". 12th **Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement (ESEM)**
- ★ 2017 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., CONTE, T., 2017, "Eliciting Strategies for the GQM+Strategies Approach in IT Service Measurement Initiatives". 11th **Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement (ESEM)**
- 2017 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., "SINIS A method to support defining goals, strategies and indicators for IT Services CTDQS Competition of Best Thesis and Dissertations about Software Quality 16th Software Quality Brazilian Conference (SBQS) (**Top 3 finalist of Best MSc Thesis Award**)
- 2015 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., "Paper about SINIS Research in Progress". WTDQS Workshop of Thesis and Dissertations about Software Quality 14th Software Quality Brazilian Conference (SBQS)
- 2015 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., "Poster about SINIS Research in Progress". AASSQ Amazon Advanced School on Software Quality 14th Software Quality Brazilian Conference (SBQS) (Best Master Degree Poster Award)

★ 2015 TRINKENREICH, B., SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., "SINIS - A Method to Select Indicators for IT Services", 16th International Conference on Product-Focused Software Process Improvement (PROFES), Bolzano, Italy, pp. 68-86. (Indicated for Best Paper Award)

2015 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., "Evaluation of incident management process under the light of MR-MPS-SV maturity model and measurement to support IT Service quality improvement", 14th Software Quality Brazilian Conference (SBQS)

2015 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., CONFORT, V., SANTORO, F., "Toward using Business Process Intelligence to Support Incident Management Measures Selection and Service Improvement". 27th International Conference Software Engineering Knowledge Engineering (SEKE)

2015 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., BARCELLOS, M., "Measures to Support IT Service Maturity Models – A Systematic Mapping Study", *17th International Conference on Enterprise Information Systems (ICEIS)*

2015 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., "Measures to Support IT Service Maturity Models – A Case Study", *17th International Conference on Enterprise Information Systems (ICEIS)*

2014 **TRINKENREICH, B.**, SANTOS, G., "Evaluation of measurement process for incidents, continuity and availability management under the light of MR-MPS-SV maturity model", 10th Annual workshop for software and services Quality improvement (WAMPS) (Best Paper Award)

Professional Certifications

- PMP: Project Management Professional (since 2009)
- •ITIL v2: IT Service Management Foundation (since 2008)
- •ITIL v3: IT Service Management Foundation (since 2013)
- •TOEFL iBT: Score 102 (2018)
- AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner Practice exam

Student Volunteer

- •International Conference on Software Maintenance and Evolution (ICSME 2020)
- •International Conference on Software and Systems Process (ICSSP 2020)
- •International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE 2021)

Other Awards (besides the papers)

- Winner of 2021 Outstanding Graduate Student award in the School of Informatics, Computing, and Cyber Systems for Spring 2021.
 - Winner of 2021 Graduate Student Government Poster Symposium Conference – Northern Arizona University
 - Finalist of 2021 Student Research Competition of International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE)
 - Nominated for 2021 Research and Creative Activity (RCA) Award Northern Arizona University

Industry Experience

- Vale S/A: IT Global Service Delivery Manager (2011-2019)
- Rede D'Or Hospitals and Health Care: PMO Member and IT Project Manager (2010-2011)
- Cyberlynxx S/A: IT Project Manager, Pre-Sales and System Admin (2000-2010)

Link to the webpages MyResearcherID and/or MyCitation (Google Scholar).

Google Scholar:	https://scholar.google.com.br/citations?hl=en&user=3nF0RuMAAAAJ
ResearcherId:	https://publons.com/researcher/4037669/bianca-trinkenreich/
DBLP:	https://dblp.org/pid/166/2138